A Guide to the Alexis Carrel papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA231
Rockefeller Archive Center
Alexis Carrel papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
1906-1957
Rockefeller Archive Center
Carrel, Alexis
Gasser, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer)
Flexner, Simon
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA231
2.64 Cubic Feet
Approximately 3 cubic feet
Biographical/Historical note
Biographical Note
1873 Born June 28, Sainte-Foy-les-Lyon
1890 L.B. University of Lyon
1891 Sc.B. University of Dijon
1896-1900 Interne des hôpitaux de Lyon
1900 M.D. University of Lyon
1900-1902 Professeur à la faculté de médecine, Université de Lyon
1905 Came to the United States
1905-1906 University of Chicago, Hull Physiological Laboratory - (type of appointment not verified, but 21 papers published with Dr. Charles C. Guthrie
1906 Fellow, The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York
1907 Assistant, RIMR
1908 Associate, RIMR
1909 Associate Member, RIMR
1912 Nobel. Prize in Medicine
1912 Member, RIMR
1913 Sc.D. Columbia University
1919 M.D. (Honorary) Belfast
1920 Sc.D. Brown University
1920 Sc.D. Princeton University
1936 LL.D. University of California
1937 Phi Beta Kappa, Dartmouth College
1937 Sc.D. University of the State of New York
1938 Sc.D. Manhattan College
1939 Member Emeritus, RIMR, Retired
1944 Died November 5, Paris, France
Numerous medal and honors and membership in many societies.
Alexis Carrel, 1873-1944, physician worked in Experimental Surgery at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research from 1906 until his retirement in 1939. The major portion of his papers were deposited by his widow, Madame Carrel, at Georgetown University Medical School.
Biography: Edwards, W. Sterling. Alexis Carrel, visionary surgeon by William Sterling Edwards and Peter D. Edwards, Springfield, Ill. Charles Thomas 1974.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of photographs of Dr. Carrel and his laboratory; laboratory alterations and war activities; bibliography and bound volumes of collected reprints; newspaper clippings and box 2 which is primarily administrative correspondence between Alexis Carrel, Simon Flexner and the Business Manager. After 1934 some correspondence is with Herbert Gasser.
Includes material relating to the Rockefeller Institute hospital established in Compiègne, France, during World War I, courses for the treatment of wounds during the war at the Rockefeller Institute's War Demonstration Hospital, and the perfusion pump designed with Charles A. Lindbergh for work in tissue culture.
Arrangement note
Correspondence arranged in chronological order.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 C232
Related Archival Materials note
See also War Demonstration Hospital records and Business Manager's Subject Files: LINDBERGH, CHARLES A.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Box 6 (Original Clipping Book) is closed to scholarly research due to its brittle and fragile condition. Box 5 Archival Copy of the Clipping Book is open and available as the access copy for researchers.
Related Materials
The Alexis Carrel papers collection is available at Georgetown University, Special Collections. Please consult an archivist for an inventory of the holdings at Georgetown.
Hospitals; Biology -- Research; Blood-vessels -- Surgery; Biochemistry; Medicine, Preventive; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Heart, Mechanical; Blood; World War I; Life sciences; Medical education; Medical research; Science -- Study and teaching; Physiology; Medical technology; Medical sciences; Carrel, Alexis; Rockefeller Institute Hospital. (Compiègne, France); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. War Demonstration Hospital; Gasser, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer); Flexner, Simon; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography 1905-1914 (Compiled in Carrel Office) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography 1916-1937 (Compiled from semi-annual lists) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical articles and sources
  - Bing, R.J. JAMA, 1983; [photocopy] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Comroe, J.H., Jr. American Review of Respiratory Disease, 1978; [photocopy] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dakin, H.D. "Notes" (ms), 1945; 4 pp. ms & 2 pp. correspondence re Dakin (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flexner, S. Memorial Minute, American Philosophical Society Yearbook, circa 1944-1945; mss, reprint (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Georgetown University Centennial Conference booklet, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Georgetown University. Index to Carrel files, photocopy (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Moseley, J. JAMA, 1980; photocopy (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Shaw, R. and Stubenford, W.T. NY State J. Med 1980, reprint (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wakler, L.C., Surgery, Gynecology, and Obstetrics. 1977, reprint (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Who Was Who, photocopy (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Witkowski, J. Medical History, 1979-1980; reprints (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Biographical mss. and notes, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence files
  - Crutcher, Katherine G. Memos, correspondence, 1944-1965 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - James, Henry
    - Sherman, William O'Neill, re Carrel method (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, Sherman ms. and reprint, circa 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous reprints, etc. re Carrel work, circa 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Smith E.B.
    - Campo, A.J. re Keith Porter use of Optical Equipment from Carrel stock, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Chesley, Leon C. re loan of Carrel-Lindbergh pump, 1945-1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Georgetown University, re gift of Carrel papers, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - van Herwerden, M.A. reprints, 1924 1926 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Clippings, 1916-1985 (Box 1, Folder 22-26)
- Carrel Writings [extra copies] (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Household insurance policies, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Motor vehicle registration, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Administrative correspondence, 1906-1946 (Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Items of special interest listed.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1906-1916 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letter to Dr. Holt requesting a grant, 1906-1916; Holograph
    - Letter accepting appointment as member of Rockefeller Institute, 1912; Holograph
    - Correspondence on arrangements to travel to Sweden to accept Nobel Prize and program honoring Carrel at Presidential reception, 1912
    - Correspondence from France on serum needs of French government; details of hospital and laboratory at Compiègne
    - Report of Harry Dakin on use of various antiseptic substances, 1915; copy
    - Carrel report: Traitement abortif de l'infection des plaies, 1915; copy
    - Correspondence on household matters
    - Report by American Fund for French wounded, "A visit to Dr. Carrel's Hospital", 1916 June
  - 1917-1922 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "What can be done for improving present condition of War surgery?" Several reports, 1918 January 14
    - Handwritten letter indication change of ideas as a result of working with wounded, 1918 August 9
    - "Experimental Surgery", 1919 March 27
    - Correspondence dealing with RI request to release Dr. Carrel to work at War Demonstration Hospital
  - 1923-1929 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence on development of microcinematography for study of cell physiology at Institute
    - Resume of projected plans for Mousery in studies of environmental effects on incidence of cancer, 1929 May 8
  - 1930-1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Handwritten letter from George M. Kober to Simon Flexner announcing choice of Alexis Carrel as 1930 recipient of Nordhoff-Jung prize for cancer research, 1930 November 25
    - Correspondence about use of Carrel's name in advertising
    - Correspondence about construction of perfusion pump apparatus and its demonstration at Congress for Experimental Cytology and loan to Carlsberg Institute, 1936 August-1937 October
      Includes drawings of various parts of the apparatus.
  - 1938-1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Assorted correspondence at time of retirement, 1938-1946 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper items reporting activities in Europe during World War II (Box 2)
    - Reports from Carrel attorney (Box 2)
    - Arrangements at Carrel death (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1936-1970; 2.5" Hollinger
  Inquiries re Carrel and Carrel's work, some "crank." Replies primarily by secretarial/administrative staff, including Miss Crutcher, E.B. Smith, Douglas Whitaker, Mabel Bright.
  - 1936 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1948-1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1957-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Guida Medica. Enciclopedia Medica per la Famiglia. 11-7-67. Vol. XII (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes cover photo of Careel-Lindbergh pump, text and additional photos on inside front cover and back cover (both sides).
- Photographs, 2.5" Hollinger (Box 4)
  - Portraits of Carrel
    - Haulenbeek, J. photographer (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Schmidt, Louis photographer (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous I and II (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - People (Individuals) (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Includes Mrs. Carrel, Mr. and Mrs. Rosenberger, Miss Crutcher, H.D. Dakin, Dr. Ebeling.
  - France World War I (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Group: Carrel and associates, undated; [print from 1945 copy negative] (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Labs, and operating rooms, General (Box 4, Folder 8)
    [See also uncataloged Laboratory photos]
  - Operating room, War Demonstration Hospital. Carrel demonstration (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous prints (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Index to Carrel portraits in NY Acad. Med. Library Catalog, 1960; 2 pp. photocopy (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Artwork: Print, "Carrel, Gallery Rockefeller Institute" by René Vincent, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  [See p. 66 for additional information and provenance].
- Caricature of Carrel by René Vincent entitled, "Carrel' Gallery Rockefeller Institute" (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Custodial History note
  Includes memo from J. Lederberg (10/12/1989) explaining that he acquired the print in Paris. Print forwarded to archives from S. Mirsky.
- Experimental notes, circa 1919 April-June; 1 folder, circa 50 pp. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Notecard attached to papers indicates that these notes were found with T. Mitchell Prudden material (probably found/identified by Ruth Sternfeld, Archivist). Observations on influence of various substances on l) rate of wound healing 2) cicatrization of wounds, in dogs.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  Addition to Papers 3 February 1986.
- Clipping Book
  - Archival Copy of Clipping Book, 1912-1925
    * refers to the number on the back of the photocopies.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 5 Archival Copy of the Clipping Book is open and available as the access copy for researchers. Box 6 (Original Clipping Book) is closed to scholarly research due to its brittle and fragile condition.
    - 1912 October-December, Pages #1 through 60* (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1912-1918, Pages #61 through 120* (Box 5, Folder 2)
      No chronological order.
    - 1917-1925, Pages # 121A through 149* (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Orignal Clipping book, 1912-1922; 1 package 15 × 9 × 2" (Box 6)
    Box 6 (Original Clipping Book) is closed to scholarly research due to its brittle and fragile condition. Box 5 Archival Copy of the Clipping Book is open and available as the access copy for researchers.
- Collected Reprints, 2 volumes
- Alexis Carrel, The Voyage to Lourdes. Translated by Virgilia Peterson, With a Preface by Charles A. Lindbergh. (New York: Harper and Brothers, 1950). 1st edition, 1 volume
  Gift of Sonya W. Mirsky, 22 October 1984.